Inventory of the James Barron Papers (1) 1776-1899
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Box 9, 1832-1834. (Box-folder 9:1-89)
  - Evaluation - Cha[rle]s Stewart, Philade[lphia], to Commodore James Barron, Comm[an]d[in]g the Navy Yard, Philade[lphia], 25 October 1834., pages. ALS, Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 9:86)
    Evaluation of the "Prow Ship" invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Francis Faior, Philade[lphia], to Captn. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 5 November 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:87)
    Thanking Barron for information regarding the steam boat.
  - Copy of a letter - [James Barron], U.S. Navy Yard, Philad[elphia], 6 November 1834., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 9:88)
    "Copy of a letter written by me for the S[ecretary] of the Navy on the pay of officers." He urges increases in Navy pay in all grades.
  - Letter - A.J. Dallas, Washington, to Com. J[ames] Barron, Washington, 18 December 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:89)
    Comment on the steam prow ship.
  Series 10: Box 10
- Box 10, 1835-1839. (Box-folder 10:1-98)
  Correspondence of the years 1835 to 1839 reflects Barron's continued involvement with his inventions. In 1835 he is able to get the patents to his cork-cutting machine and his pump extended by an Act of Congress, 15 January. He continued his attempts to have the Navy adopt his "bellows ventilation for removing foul air from the vessels" and his "steam prow for warships," and worked with Amos Kendall on the perfecting of a cylinder steam propulsion system for ships. Other inventions which he continued to perfect were the new type wind mill, the floating dry dock, a ship's galley, and a gun carriage. He was interested in bringing out a new edition of naval instructions for flag signals, a system which he first reorganized in 1798.
  In 1836, "when war was considered inevitable," he appealed to President Jackson to give him the command of a ship or to give him an order to build his steam prow war ship, 5 January. In 1837 he resigned his naval command, the Philadelphia Naval Yard, because an officer junior to him had been appointed President of the Navy Board, 6 June. The next year there is a rumor that he is to assume the Presidency of the Board, 20 November 1838; and in 1839 he moves again, this time to Germantown, Pennsylvania, 27 July 1839.
  Included are letters concerned with the Revolutionary War, service of Barron and his father, of Barron's commercial command of the ship Portia, which was held in a Danish port by the outbreak of the War of 1812, and with the court martial of Comm. J.D. Elliott, 5 December 1839.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Washington, to Samuel Bell, Member of the Judiciary Committee of the Senate of the U.S., 9 January 1835., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 10:1)
    Re: the cork cutting machine and the pump invented by Barron.
  - J.D. Elliott, Navy Yard, Boston, to Commodore [James] Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 14 January 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:2)
    Re: the opposition of the local whig party to him as a Jackson man.
  - Letter - J[ames] Barron, Washington, to Mahlon Dickerson, Secretary of the Navy, 15 January 1835., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:3)
    Re: the claim of John Thompson.
  - Bill - "A BILL To extend two patents of James Barron." 15 January 1835., 2 pages. PM. (Box-folder 10:4)
    Re: the pump and cork-cutter.
  - Petition - to Congress for a renewal of patents for pump and cork cutter [by James Barron], [January 1835]., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Letter - Mrs. M[ary] A. B[lake], Fredericksburg, [Virginia], to James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 2 February 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Letter - Philemon [Gatewood], Norfolk, to Comr. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 4 February 1835., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:7)
    Re: an order on him from Taylor.
  - Letter - James Barron to the House of Representatives, 4 February 1835., 15 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:8)
    Re: the steam prow war ship.
  - Receipt - to James Barron, U.S. Navy, for a deposit for the patent on "Bellows Ventilation for removing foul air from Vessels," signed Geo[rge] M. Davis, 6 February 1835., 1 page. PADS. (Box-folder 10:9)
  - Account - of Commo. [James] Barron with "Brown's Indian Queen Hotel, Washington City" signed F. Hume for J. Brown, 11 February 1835., 1 page. PADS. (Box-folder 10:10)
    Letterhead has engraving of the hotel front.
  - Letter - Isaac Coffin, Chettenham, to Commodore [James] Barron, Philadelphia, 17 February 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:11)
    Re: a portrait of Barron.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Philadelphia, to [?], 7 February 1835., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 10:12)
    Re: wind mill improved by Barron.
  - Letter - Tho[ma]s William Earle, Liverpool, to Commodore [James] Barron, Philadelphia, 26 February 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:13)
    Enclosing a letter from Adm. Sir Isaac Coffin Bart.
  - Letter - Ade. Martini, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 27 February 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:14)
    Re: steam prow ship.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Phi[ladelphia], to Monsieur Martini, Washington, 6 March 1835., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:15)
  - Letters - Amos Kendall, Washington, to Commo. James Barron, Washington and Philadelphia, March-April 1835., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:16)
    Re: the sharing of profits on the invention of the cylinder steam boat and plans for building such a craft.
  - Letters - [James Barron], Philadelphia, to Amos Kendall, March-July 1835., 2 letters. ADrs. (Box-folder 10:17)
    Re: the cylinder steam boat.
  - Request - J.J. Martinez, Madrid, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, 20 April 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:18)
    Requesting the plans of the U.S. Ship John Adams to serve as a model for war ships being built by Spain.
  - Letters - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, May-October 1835., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:19)
    Family letters, including notice of the death of Mrs. Pendergast, the daughter of Barron, and of Barron's grandchild.
  - Letter - [James Barron], to Com. J. Biddle, 17 June 1835., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 10:20)
    Re: the model of a boat which is to be built.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Ph[iladelph]ia, to Colo[nel] Tompkins, 19 June 1835., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 10:21)
    Re: Revolutionary War claims.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Philad[elphia], to Judge Porter, 24 June 1835., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 10:22)
    Re: patent rights to the pump invented by Barron.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Philadelphia, to the N[avy] Com[mittee], 5 July 1835., 2 ADrs. (Box-folder 10:23)
    Re: problems of armed steam vessels.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Phil[adelphia], to M. Dickerson, 7 July 1835., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 10:24)
    Re: on the subject of armed steam vessels.
  - Account - of Commodore James Barron with Emma Prevost, 4 September 1835., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 10:25)
  - Account - of Com[m]odore J[ames] Barron at the Blue Bell, signed by John Hall, 5 September 1835., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 10:26)
  - Account - of Commodore [James] Barron with Frederick Brown's Drug and Chemical Store, Philad[elphi]a. ADS. 1 p. Engraving of the interior of the store is on the letterhead. 17 September 1835., pages. (Box-folder 10:27)
  - Philemon G[atewood], U.S. Rev. Cutter Dallas, Baltimore, to Com. James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 9 November 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:28)
    Re: War bounties which have run out because of lapsed time.
  - Letter - [James Barron] to [H.A. Mix], 7 December 1835., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 10:29)
    Re: pay of ship masters.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Washington, to Leonard Jarvis, Chairman of the Naval Committee, 15 December 1835., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:30)
    Re: letter of Capt. [H.A.] Mix of the Navy.
  - Letter - James Barron, Wash[ington], to Balie Payton, 28[?] December 1835., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:31)
    Re: the renewal of patents on the cork cutter and pump.
  - Account - A printed account of the claims on Virginia for naval service in the Revolutionary War, made "for the other Heirs and Himself, James Barron.", [1835]., 1 page. PM. (Box-folder 10:32)
  - Appeal - James Barron "to General Andrew Jackson, President of the U.S. & Commander in Chief of the Military and Naval forces thereof," 5 January 1836., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:33)
    An appeal for the command of a ship or permission to build his steam prow warship "when a war was considered inevitable."
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Washington, to Elisha Whittlesey, Chairman of Committee of Claims, H[ouse] of R[epresentatives], 16 January 1836., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:34)
    Re: the case of John Thompson.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Wash[ington], to John Taliaferro, 8 February 1836., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:35)
    Re: Barron's business before the Committee of Claims.
  - Letter - M.P. Gillis, Philadelphia, to Commo. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington City, 9 February 1836., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:36)
    Re: need for the increase in the Navy.
  - Letter - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 24 February 1836., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:37)
    Norfolk news.
  - Estimate - W[illia]m E. [?], Washington, 4 March 1836., AD. (Box-folder 10:38)
    "Estimate for a floating dock for repairing Schooners of 175 tons burthen."
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], W[ashington], to Eli Moore, 4 March 1836., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:39)
    A reference to [Henry A.] Wise.
  - Letter - H.M. Prevost, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 7 March 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:40)
    Re: money sent from Mr. Pendergast, Barron's son-in-law.
  - Letter - E. Shubrick, Charleston, to Commodore [James] Barron, Com[man]d[in]g N[avy] Yard, Philadelphia, 20 March 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:41)
    Re: floating dry dock invented by Barron.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], P[hiladelphia], to Andrew T. Judson, 26 March 1836., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:42)
    Re: a new type of dock.
  - Receipt - Henry L. Ellsworth, Patent Office, to Com. James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 8 September 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:43)
    Receipt for the model of the floating dock invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Nichs. I. Keefe, U.S. Ship Hudson, New York, to James Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 13 September 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:44)
    Appreciation for Barron's interest in him.
  - Power of Attorney - [James Barron], U.S. Navy Yard, Ph[iladelphi]a, to Judge Tompkins, Glasgow, Barren County, Kentucky, 19 October 1836., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 10:45)
    Power of attorney for land claims.
  - Receipt - A.B. Ellison, U.S. Navy Yard, New York, to Commodore James Barron, Commanding U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 1 November 1836., 1 page. PADS. (Box-folder 10:46)
    Receipt for the description of a valve-board pump.
  - Letter - Mary Elliott, Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to Commre. James Barron, Commanding U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 10 November 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:47)
    Appreciation for a portrait.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Flag Ship Peacock, Marathan, Lower California, to Comdr. John Rodgers, Pres. of the Board of N[avy] C[ommissioners], Washington, 14 November 1836., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:48)
    Accounts of experiments made with bellows invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Marathan, Gulph [sic] of California, U.S.S. Peacock, to Comdre. James Barron, U. States Navy, Philadelphia, 16 November 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:48)
    Signs self as commanding the East India and Asia [?].
  - Receipt - W.L. Ellsworth, Patent Office, to Como. James Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 25 November 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:49)
    Receipt for "additional remarks on your galley."
  - Letter - Jacob P. Giraud, New York, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 13 December 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:50)
    Re: samples of cork.
  - Petition - James Barron, Philadelphia, "to the Honorable Senate and House of Representatives of the United States of America, in Congress assembled." 19 December 1836., 2 copies. ADrsS. (Box-folder 10:51)
    Petition concerning the Navy signals which Barron first reorganized in 1798 and 1799.
  - Letter - Lt. Jno. P. Gillis, Springfield, Illinois, to Commo. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 7 January 1837., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:52)
    Enclosing a sketch of "Floating Dry Dock at Smithland on the Ohio River, mouth of Cumberland."
  - Letters - Ch. A. Grice, Portsmouth, Virginia, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, January-March 1837., 5 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:53)
    Re: the galley invented by Barron.
  - Letters - Lt. James Glynn, U.S. Barque Consort, Norfolk, Virginia, to Commo. James Barron, Com[mandin]g Navy Yard, Philadelphia, January-June 1837., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:54)
    Re: a galley invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Henry A. Wise, Washington, to Com. James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 5 February 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:55)
    Re: the "Bill reported for the Ventilator" [to Congress].
  - Invitation - to Com. [James] Barron from Colonel Page. 8 March 1837., PAM, C. (Box-folder 10:56)
  - Jno. Rodgers, Navy Commander's Office, to Sam[ue]l Humphrey, Chief Naval Contractor, Washington, 17 March 1837., 2 pages. Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 10:57)
    Re: repairs to U.S. Ship Pennsylvania.
  - Letters - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, March-October 1837., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:58)
    Family and other news from Norfolk, including reaction to his resignation from the command of the Navy Yard in Philadelphia.
  - Letter - Mrs. Frances Elliott, Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to Comd. James Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 1 May 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:59)
    Appreciation for a box sent her by Barron.
  - Letter - James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, to Amos Kendall, 5 May 1837., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:60)
    Re: the rumor that Comm. Rodgers has resigned the presidency of the Board of Naval Commissioners and that an officer junior to Barron may be appointed to the position.
  - Request - Lewis J. Cist, Cincinnati, [Ohio], to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 29 May 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:61)
    Request for an autograph for his collection.
  - Resignation - J[ames] B[arron], Philadelphia, Navy Yard, to James Buchanan, Lancaster, Pennsylvania, 6 June 1837., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:62)
    Resigning his command because a junior officer who has served him as a Lieutenant is being placed over him.
  - Letter - J.W. Hand, Patent Office, to Commodore Ja[me]s Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 19 June 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:63)
    Re: the patent for the floating dry dock.
  - Account - T. Brick & Co., Phila[delphia], to Com. [James] Barron, 22 June 1837., 1 page. ADS. (Box-folder 10:64)
    An account sheet.
  - Letter - Henry S. Crabbe, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, 1 July 1837., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:65)
    A farewell letter as Barron left the command of the Yard.
  - Letter - James Barron, Philadelphia, to R. Kennedy, W. Myers, W. Vinyard, John Southall, A. Powell, W.T. Donaldson, H.S. Crabbe, H. Snyder, B. Fitzimons, A. Levy, and J.D. Anderson, 5 July 1837., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:66)
    Appreciation for an affectionate letter of farewell from these.
  - Letter - James Barron, Philadelphia, to W.W. McKean and 22 others, 5 July 1837., 2 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:67)
    Appreciation of a letter of farewell from these.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Philadelphia, to Frederick Vincent, 17 September 1837., AL, ADr. (Box-folder 10:68)
    Re: Miles King.
  - Letter - Henry A. Wise, Washington, to Com. James Barron, City of Philadelphia, 3 October 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:69)
    Re: his readiness to act in Barron's behalf.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Ph[iladelph]ia, to Henry A. Wise, 9 October 1837., 2 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:70)
    Complaining about his treatment by the Navy.
  - Receipt - to Commodore [James] Barron from Carey & Hart, Booksellers, Philadelphia, 17 November 1837., PADS. (Box-folder 10:71)
    For Life of Burr.
  - Letter - Lt. [S.W.] Godon, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 16 December 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:72)
    Re: articles and letters received for Barron after his departure from Philadelphia.
  - Henry S. Crabbe, U.S. Navy Yard, Philad[elphi]a, to Comm. James Barron, 26 December 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:73)
    Re: gun carriage invented by Barron.
  - Letter - F. Mallory, Washington, to Comm. James Barron, Norfolk, Virg[ini]a, 14 January 1838., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:74)
    Offering his assistance needed by Barron that he can render.
  - Letter - Lawrence Myers, Philad[elphi]a, to Comdr. James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 27 January 1838., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:75)
    Re: stoves left by Barron.
  - Letters - Lt. S.W. Godon, Philadelphia and New York, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Norfolk, Virginia, February-March 1838., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:76)
  - Letter - A. B. Pinkham, Portsmouth, to Com. James Barron, 21 March 1838., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:77)
    Introducing Capt. Von Shanter of the Russian Imperial Navy.
  - Letter - James Ferguson, Philadelphia Navy Yard, to Commodore James Barron, 2 April 1838., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:78)
    Re: the conditions of (sailing) Masters in the Navy and a memorial on the subject which was before Congress.
  - Letter - Henry A. Wise, Washington, to Comm. James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 2 April 1838., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:79)
    Re: "my connexion [sic] with that unhappy duel."
  - John L. and Lavinia Watson, Germantown, [Pennsylvania], to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 9 April 1838., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:80)
    Re: the Polar Expedition and regret at Barron's leaving Philadelphia.
  - Letter - Mrs. J[ane Barron] Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], to her sister, Mrs. [Virginia] S.V. Pendergrast, Washington City, 1 June 1838., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:81)
    Family affairs, with greetings to her father, James Barron.
  - Letter - H.S. Crabbe, U.S. Navy Yard, Philad[elphi]a, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 8 June 1838., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:82)
    Re: the gun carriage and steam vessels.
  - Account - of Como. [James] Barron with Thomas Purcell, Washington, 29 June 1838., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:83)
  - Letters - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, June-August 1838., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:84)
    Re: family and Norfolk affairs.
  - Report - J.D. Elliott, U.S.S. Constitution, Ham[pton] Roads, Norfolk, to J.A. Pauling, [Secretary of the Navy], 31 July 1838., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:85)
    A report at the end of a cruise of three years and six months.
  - Letter - Lt. and Mrs. S.G. Pendergast, Charleston, [Massachuetts], to her father, Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington City, 25 September 1838., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:86)
  - Complaints - J.D. Elliott, U.S.S. Constitution and Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to Como. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, September-November 1838., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:87)
    Complaining against continued slander in the newspapers.
  - Letter - Frederick Vincent, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington City, 26 October 1838., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:88)
    Re: the services of Barron's father in the Revolutionary War.
  - Letter - J.K. Paulding, Navy Department, to Comde. Jesse D. Elliott, U.S. Navy, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, 15 November 1838., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:89)
    Re: the importing of Jack Asses by the Commanders of Squadrons.
  - Application - Capt. W[illia]m Gatewood, New York, to Com. James Barron, U.S. Navy, 20 November 1838., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:90)
    Applying for the position of chief clerk for Barron when he becomes President of the Navy Board. Enclosed: newspaper clipping announcing the rumor that Barron is to be appointed President of the Navy Board.
  - Letter - [J.D. Elliott], Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to J.K. Paulding, [Secretary of the Navy], 27 November 1838., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 10:91)
    Explanation for the importation of "Jack Asses and other animals." Enclosure: "Extract from Hon. Sam'l L. Southard," signed Dan[ie]l F. Patten. Re: animals, seeds, and plants.
  - Report - Jno. P. Gillis, U.S. Ship North Carolina, Callao, to Commo. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Norfolk, Virginia, 28 November 1838., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:92)
    Report on the political situation in South America.
  - Complaint - J.D. Elliott, Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to Com. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, 1 December 1838., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:93)
    Complaints about the Navy Board.
  - Letters - J.D. Elliott, Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to Com. James Barron, Washington, D.C. and Germantown, [Pennsylvania], January-December 1839., 6 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 10:94)
    Re: troubles that Elliott had experienced on his last cruise with his officers and Marines; of the conflict that he was having with Mr. Paulding, Secretary of the Navy; and of rumors of arrangements for the trial of Elliott.
  - Statement - James Barron, Washington, 3 February 1839., 2 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 10:95)
    A statement regarding his claims on the Navy.
  - Letter - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Washington, D.C., 7 February 1839., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 10:96)
    Re: the death of his son, Philemon.
  - Complaints - W[illia]m Gatewood, New York, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington City, March 1839., 2 letters. AlsS. (Box-folder 10:97)
    Complaints about his treatment by the Navy; and valuable information on the " Portia," the commercial ship captained by Barron which was held in Copenhagen by the outbreak of the War of 1812.
  - Letter - Edward Dyem, Washington City, "To All Whom it May Concern," 27 July 1839., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 10:98)
    A note sent with "Judy, a colored woman," who is proceeding to Germantown, [Pennsylvania], where she is to be the servant of Commodore James Barron and family.
  Series 11: Box 11
- Box 11, 1840-1851 (Box-folder 11:1-103)
  The correspondence of 1840 to Barron's death in 1851, covers the years in which he assumed his last command in the Navy. Living in Germantown, outside of Philadelphia, he sought a position of Naval command under Presidents Harrison and Tyler. On 31 March 1842, he assumed command of the Naval Asylum in Philadelphia (a home for retired men of the Navy). In that position he also supervised training and examination of Midshipmen. When G.P. Upshur, then Secretary of the Navy, organized the Naval Academy in Annapolis, he wrote to Barron for advice on training and examinations as they had been held under him, 17 July 1847. On 30 November 1842 Barron retired from the command of the Naval Asylum and in 1845 moved back to Norfolk where he built a house for his retirement at the age of 77. There is much correspondence in this period in regard to Revolutionary War bounty lands and pensions: in 1848 Barron was recognized as the Senior Officer in the Navy, having been made Captain in May 1799.